Now the tidings were repeated,
Jo oli sanoma saatu,
And the news was widely rumoured,
viety viesti tuonnemmaksi
How the youthful maid had perished,
neien nuoren nukkumasta,
And the fair one had departed.
kaunihin katoamasta.
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen,
Deeply sorrowed at the tidings;
tuo tuosta pahoin pahastui:
Wept at evening, wept at morning,
itki illat, itki aamut,
Spent the livelong night in weeping,
yöhyet enemmin itki,
For the fair one who had perished,
kun oli kaunis kaatununna,
For the maiden who had slumbered,
neitonen nukahtanunna,
In the muddy lake downsunken
mennyt lietohon merehen,
To the depths below the billows.
alle aaltojen syvien.
Then he went, in sorrow sighing,
Astui huollen, huokaellen,
While his heart was filled with anguish,
syämellä synkeällä
To the blue lake's rocky margin,
rannalle meren sinisen.
And he spoke the words which follow:
Sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"Tell me, Untamo, thou sleeper,
"Sano nyt, Untamo, unesi,
Tell me all thy dreams, O idler,
maku'usi, maan venyjä:
Where to find the realm of Ahto,
missä Ahtola asuvi,
Where dwell Vellamo's fair maidens?"
neiot Vellamon venyvi?"
Sleeper Untamo made answer,
Sanoipa Untamo unensa,
And his dreams he thus repeated:
maku'unsa maan venyjä:
"There has Ahto fixed his country,
"Tuolla Ahtola asuvi,
There dwell Vellamo's fair maidens,
neiot Vellamon venyvi.
Near the cloud-encompassed headland,
Nenässä utuisen niemen,
Near the ever-misty island,
päässä saaren terhenisen
In the depths below the billows,
alla aaltojen syvien,
On the black ooze at the bottom.
päällä mustien mutien.
"There has Ahto fixed his country,
"Siellä Ahtola asuvi,
There dwell Vellamo's fair maidens,
neiot Vellamon venyvi
Living in a narrow chamber,
pikkuisessa pirttisessä,
In a little room abiding,
kamarissa kaitaisessa,
With the walls of varied marble,
kiven kirjavan kylessä,
In the depths beside the headland."
paaen paksun kainalossa."
Then the aged Väinämöinen
Siitä vanha Väinämöinen
Hastened to his little vessel,
vetihe venesijoille.
And he scanned his fishing-tackle,
Silmeävi siimojansa,
And his hooks with care inspected;
katselevi onkiansa;
Put the tackle in his pocket,
otti ongen taskuhunsa,
And the barbed hooks in his wallet.
väkärauan väskyhynsä.
Through the waves his boat he ferried,
Soutoa melastelevi,
Making for the jutting headland,
päähän saaren saauttavi,
To the cape, with clouds encompassed,
nenähän utuisen niemen,
And the ever-misty island.
päähän saaren terhenisen.
Then he set about his fishing,
Siin' oli ongella olija,
And he watched his angle closely,
aina siimalla asuja,
And he held his hand-net ready,
käeksellä kääntelijä.
Dropped his angle in the water,
Laski launihin merelle,
And he fished, and tried his fortune,
ongitteli, orhitteli:
While the rod of copper trembled,
vapa vaskinen vapisi,
And the thread of silver whistled,
hope'inen siima siukui,
And the golden line whirred loudly.
nuora kultainen kulisi.
And at length one day it happened,
Jo päivänä muutamana,
Very early in the morning,
huomenna moniahana
On his hook a fish was hanging,
kala otti onkehensa,
And a salmon-trout was captured.
taimen takrarautahansa.
In the boat he drew it quickly,
Sen veti venosehensa,
And upon the planks he cast it.
talui talkapohjahansa.
Then he scanned the fish, and turned it,
Katselevi, kääntelevi.
And he spoke the words which follow;
Sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"'Tis a fish, among the fishes,
"Onp' on tuo kala kalanen,
For I never saw its equal,
kun en tuota tunnekana!
Smoother is it than a powan,
Sileähk' on siikaseksi,
Than a salmon-trout more yellow,
kuleahka kuujaseksi,
Greyer than a pike I deem it,
haleahka haukiseksi,
For a female fish too finless,
evätöin emäkalaksi;
For a male 'tis far too scaleless;
ihala imehnoksiki,
Has no tresses, like a maiden,
päärivatoin neitoseksi,
Nor, like water-nymphs, 'tis belted;
vyötöin veen on tyttöseksi,
Nor is earless like a pigeon;
korvitoin kotikanaksi:
It resembles most a salmon,
luopuisin meriloheksi,
Or a perch from deepest water."
syvän aallon ahveneksi."
In his waistband Väinämöinen
Vyöll' on veitsi Väinämöisen,
Bore a case-knife, silver-hafted,
pää hopea huotrasessa.
And he drew the knife of sharpness.
Veti veitsen viereltänsä,
Drew the case-knife, silver-hafted,
huotrastansa pää hopean
And prepared to slit the salmon,
kalan palstoin pannaksensa,
And to cut the fish to pieces,
lohen leikkaellaksensa
Thought to eat it for his breakfast.
aamuisiksi atrioiksi,
Or a snack to make his luncheon,
murkinaisiksi muruiksi,
To provide him with a dinner,
lohisiksi lounahiksi,
And a plenteous supper likewise.
iltaruoiksi isoiksi.
As he would have slit the salmon.
Alkoi lohta leikkaella,
And would cut the fish to pieces,
veitsen viilteä kaloa:
Sprang the salmon in the water,
lohi loimahti merehen,
For the beauteous fish jumped sideways
kala kirjo kimmeltihe
From the planking of the red boat,
pohjasta punaisen purren,
From the boat of Väinämöinen.
venehestä Väinämöisen.
Thereupon her head she lifted,
Äsken päätänsä ylenti,
Raised her shoulders from the water,
oikeata olkapäätä
On the fifth wave's watery hillock,
vihurilla viiennellä,
From the sixth high wave emerging,
kupahalla kuuennella;
Then her hands in air uplifted,
nosti kättä oikeata,
And displayed her left foot also,
näytti jalkoa vasenta
When the seventh wave roses upswelling,
seitsemännellä selällä,
And upon the ninth wave's summit.
yheksännen aallon päällä.
Thereupon the fish addressed him,
Sieltä tuon sanoiksi virkki,
And it spoke, and thus protested:
itse lausui ja pakisi:
"O thou aged Väinämöinen,
"Oi sie vanha Väinämöinen!
Surely I have not come hither,
En ollut minä tuleva
Like a salmon, to be slaughtered,
lohi leikkaellaksesi,
Or a fish, to cut to pieces,
kala palstoin pannaksesi,
Only to become your breakfast,
aamuisiksi atrioiksi,
Or a snack to make your luncheon,
murkinaisiksi muruiksi,
To provide you with a dinner.
lohisiksi lounahiksi,
And a plenteous supper likewise."
iltaruoiksi isoiksi."
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"Wherefore didst thou then come hither?"
"Miksi sie olit tuleva?"
"Therefore 'tis that I have sought thee,
"Olinpa minä tuleva
In thine arm like dove to nestle,
kainaloiseksi kanaksi,
By thy side to sit for ever,
ikuiseksi istujaksi,
On thy knee, as consort sitting,
polviseksi puolisoksi,
To prepare the couch to rest thee,
sijasi levittäjäksi,
And to smooth thy pillow for thee,
päänalaisen laskijaksi,
Keep thy little room in order,
pirtin pienen pyyhkijäksi,
And to sweep the flooring for thee,
lattian lakaisijaksi,
In thy room to light the fire,
tulen tuojaksi tupahan,
And to fan the flames up brightly,
valkean virittäjäksi,
There large loaves of bread to bake thee,
leivän paksun paistajaksi,
Cakes of honey to prepare thee,
mesileivän leipojaksi,
And thy jug of beer to fill thee,
olutkannun kantajaksi,
And thy dinner set before thee.
atrian asettajaksi.
"I am not a water-salmon,
"En ollut merilohia,
Not a perch from deepest water,
syvän aallon ahvenia:
But a young and lovely maiden,
olin kapo, neiti nuori,
Youthful Joukahainen's sister,
sisar nuoren Joukahaisen,
Whom thou all thy life hast longed for,
kuta pyyit kuun ikäsi,
Whom thou hast so long desired.
puhki polvesi halasit.
"O thou pitiful old creature,
"Ohoh, sinua, ukko utra,
Väinämöinen, void of wisdom,
vähämieli Väinämöinen,
Thou hadst not the wit to hold me,
kun et tuntenut piteä
Vellamo's young water-maiden,
Vellamon vetistä neittä,
Me, the darling child of Ahto!"
ahon lasta ainokaista!"
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen
Head bowed down, and deeply grieving,
alla päin, pahoilla mielin:
"Sister thou of Joukahainen,
"Oi on sisar Joukahaisen!
Once again return, I pray thee."
Toki tullos toinen kerta!"
But she never more came near him,
Eip' on toiste tullutkana,
Ne'er again throughout his lifetime;
ei toiste sinä ikänä:
For she turned away, and, diving,
jo vetihe, vierähtihe,
Vanished from the water's surface
ve'en kalvosta katosi
Down among the rocks so varied,
kiven kirjavan sisähän,
In a liver-coloured crevice.
maksankarvaisen malohon.
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Pondered deeply, and reflected,
tuo on tuossa arvelevi,
What to do, and what was needful
miten olla, kuin eleä.
Quick he wove a net all silken,
Jo kutaisi sulkkunuotan,
And he drew it straight and crossways,
veti vettä ristin rastin,
Through the reach, and then across it,
salmen pitkin, toisen poikki;
Drew it through the quiet waters,
veti vienoja vesiä,
Through the depths beloved by salmons
lohiluotojen lomia,
And through Väinölä's deep waters.
noita Väinölän vesiä,
And by Kalevala's sharp headlands,
Kalevalan kannaksia,
Through the deep, dark watery caverns,
synkkiä syväntehiä,
And the wide expanse of water,
suuria selän napoja,
And through Joukola's great rivers,
Joukolan jokivesiä,
And across the bays of Lapland.
Lapin lahtirantasia.
Other fish he caught in plenty,
Sai kyllin kaloja muita,
All the fishes of the waters,
kaikkia ve'en kaloja,
Only not the fish he sought for,
ei saanut sitä kalaista,
Which he kept in mind for ever,
mitä mielensä pitävi:
Never Vellamo's fair maiden,
Vellamon vetistä neittä,
Not the dearest child of Ahto.
ahon lasta ainokaista.
Then the aged Väinämöinen,
Siitä vanha Väinämöinen
Bowed his head, lamenting deeply,
alla päin, pahoilla mielin,
With his cap adjusted sideways,
kaiken kallella kypärin
And he spoke the words which follow:
itse tuon sanoiksi virkki:
"O how grievous is my folly,
"Ohoh, hullu, hulluuttani,
Weak am I in manly wisdom,
vähämieli, miehuuttani!
Once indeed was understanding,
Olipa minulla mieltä,
Insight too conferred upon me,
ajatusta annettuna,
And my heart was great within me;
syäntä suurta survottuna,
Such in former times my portion.
oli ennen aikoinansa.
But in days that now are passing.
Vaanpa nyt tätä nykyä,
In the evil days upon me,
tällä inhalla iällä,
Now my strength with age is failing,
puuttuvalla polveksella
All my understanding weakens
kaikki on mieli melkeässä,
And my insight has departed,
ajatukset arvoisessa,
All my judgment is perverted.
kaikki toimi toisialla.
"She for whom long years I waited,
"Kuta vuotin kuun ikäni,
Whom for half my life I longed for,
kuta puolen polveani,
Vellamo's fair water-maiden,
Vellamon vetistä neittä,
Youngest daughter of the surges.
veen on viimeistä tytärtä
Who should be my friend for ever,
ikuiseksi ystäväksi,
And my wife throughout my lifetime,
polviseksi puolisoksi,
Came and seized the bait I offered,
se osasi onkeheni,
In my boat sprang unresisting,
vierähti venoseheni:
But I knew not how to hold her,
minä en tuntenut piteä,
To my home I could not take her,
en kotihin korjaella,
But she plunged amid the waters,
laskin jälle lainehisin,
Diving to the depths profoundest."
alle aaltojen syvien!"
Then he wandered on a little,
Meni matkoa vähäisen,
And he walked, in sadness sighing,
astui huollen, huokaellen;
To his home direct returning,
kulkevi kotia kohti.
And he spoke the words which follow:
Sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"Once indeed the birds were singing,
"Kukkui muinaiset käkeni,
And my joyous cuckoo hailed me,
entiset ilokäkeni,
Both at morning and at evening,
kukkui ennen illoin, aamuin,
Likewise, too, in midday hours.
kerran keskipäivälläki:
What has stilled their lively music,
mikä nyt sorti suuren äänen,
And has hushed their charming voices?
äänen kaunihin kaotti?
Care has stilled their lively music,
Suru sorti suuren äänen,
Sorrow checked their cheerful voices,
huoli armahan alenti;
Therefore do they sing no longer,
sill' ei kuulu kukkuvaksi,
Neither at the sun's declining,
päivän laskun laulavaksi
To rejoice me in the evening,
minun iltani iloksi,
Nor to cheer me in the morning.
huomeneni huopeheksi.
"Now no more can I consider
"Enkä nyt tuota tieäkänä
How to shape my course of action,
miten olla, kuin eleä,
How upon the earth to sojourn,
tällä ilmalla asua,
How throughout the world to travel.
näillä mailla matkaella.
Would my mother now were living,
Oisiko emo elossa,
And my aged mother waking!
vanhempani valvehella,
She would surely tell me truly
sepä saattaisi sanoa,
How to best support my trouble,
miten pystössä pysyä,
That my grief may not o'erwhelm me,
murehisin murtumatta,
And my sorrow may not crush me,
huolihin katoamatta
In these weary days of evil,
näissä päivissä pahoissa,
In this time of deep depression."
ape'issa miel'aloissa!"
In her grave his mother wakened,
Emo hauasta havasi,
Answered from beneath the billows:
alta aallon vastaeli:
"Still thy mother lives and hears thee,
"Viel' onpi emo elossa,
And thy aged mother wakens,
vanhempasi valvehella,
That she plainly may advise thee.
joka saattavi sanoa,
How to best support thy trouble.
miten olla oikeana,
That thy grief may not o'erwhelm thee,
murehisin murtumatta,
And thy sorrow may not crush thee,
huolihin katoamatta
In these weary days of evil,
niissä päivissä pahoissa,
In these days of deep depression.
ape'issa miel'aloissa:
Seek thou out the maids of Pohja,
mene Pohjan tyttärihin!
Where the daughters are more handsome,
Siell' on tyttäret somemmat,
And the maidens twice as lovely,
neiet kahta kaunihimmat,
And are five or six times nimbler,
viittä, kuutta virkeämmät,
Not like lazy girls of Jouko,
ei Joukon jorottaria,
Lapland's fat and sluggish daughters.
Lapin lapsilönttäreitä.
"Thence a wife, O son, provide thee,
"Sieltä naios, poikaseni,
From the fairest maids of Pohja;
paras Pohjan tyttäristä,
Choose a maid of fair complexion,
jok' on sievä silmiltänsä,
Lovely, too, in every feature,
kaunis katsannoisiltansa,
One whose feet are always nimble,
aina joutuisa jalalta
Always active in her movements."
sekä liukas liikunnolta!"